TONY DI SERA

4721 Sycamore Drive Holladay, UT 84117 tonyads@genetics.utah.edu

801.554.2312 https://github.com/tonydisera

I am a data scientist and software developer in bioinformatics specializing in real-time analysis and visualization. My current work focuses on diagnosing rare inheritance diseases through genomic variant discovery and cancer genomic analysis. To learn more about my work, visit http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/~tonydisera/profile/.

EXPERIENCE

University of Utah, Dept of Human Genetics

Senior Web Developer 2014 – Present

Developed real-time genomic visualizations for the web, including QC app that shows various metrics on a VCF (variant control format) file http://vcf.iobio.io and an application for performing real-time variant discovery http://gene.iobio.io. This app streams data to services which annotate variants with functional impact, protein prediction, allele frequency, and regulatory elements.

Currently working on a deep learning model to predict cancer drug response from tumor somatic mutations, copy number variations, and gene expression.

Huntsman Cancer Institute

Senior Software Developer 2004 - 2014

Co-developer of BioMiner, a tool that queries ChIP Seq, RNA Seq, Bisulfite Seq, and Variant analysis based on region and gene-based criteria. Results provide information about analysis and samples with links to visualize data tracks in IGV genome browser.

Principle developer of GNomEx, a LIMs and Analysis Project repository for high throughput sequencing facilities. Software tracks genomic experiments from ordering through results delivery and downstream analysis. Responsibilities include leading team of 4 developers and working closely with core facility managers and bioinformatics analysts to provide technical solutions that keep pace with fast-changing, ever expanding needs.

Utah Genome Project, Cimarron Software

Software Developer 1994 - 2004

Developed a framework for laboratory management. Developed general purpose Ad hoc reporting application that allows the end-user to enter search criteria and generate queries with intuitive user interface which hides the complexity of the underlying relational database.

EDUCATION

UC Berkeley (currently enrolled) -- Master of Data Science program UC Berkeley GPA – 3.96

Bachelor of Science - DeVry University

1982-1986

GPA – 4.0, Student of the Year 1985, Presidential Honor Society, Epsilon Delta Pi

PUBLICATIONS

Ekawade A, Velinder M, Ward A, **DiSera T**, Miller C, Qiao Y, Marth G, "Genepanel.iobio - an easy to use web tool for generating disease- and phenotype-associated gene lists" BMC Medical Genomics 12:190, PMID: 31829207

Ostrander BEP, Butterfield RJ, Pedersen BS, Farrell AJ, Layer RM, Ward A, Miller C, **DiSera** T, Filloux FM, <u>Candee MS</u>, Newcomb T, <u>Bonkowsky JL</u>, Marth GT, Quinlan AR. "Wholegenome analysis for effective clinical diagnosis and gene discovery in early infantile epileptic encephalopathy." NPJ Genome Med. 2018; 3: 22.

Ward, Alistair, Mary A. Karren, **Tonya Di Sera**, Chase Miller, Matt Velinder, Yi Qiao, Francis M. Filloux, et al. 2017. "Rapid Clinical Diagnostic Variant Investigation of Genomic Patient Sequencing Data with Iobio Web Tools." Journal of Clinical and Translational Science 1 (6): 381–86.

Layer, Ryan M., Brent S. Pedersen, **Tonya DiSera**, Gabor T. Marth, Jason Gertz, and Aaron R. Quinlan. 2018. "GIGGLE: A Search Engine for Large-Scale Integrated Genome Analysis." Nature Methods 15 (2): 123–26.

Yi Qiao, **Tonya DiSera**, Brian D'Astous, and Gabor T. Marth. 2014. "Bam.iobio: A Web-Based, Real-Time, Sequence Alignment File Inspector." Nature Methods 11 (12): 1189.

Nix DA, **Di Sera TL**, Dalley BK, Milash BA, Cundick RM, Quinn KS, Courdy SJ: Next generation tools for genomic data generation, distribution, and visualization. BMC Bioinformatics 2010, 11:455